Perfect.
All right.
Well, thank you all very much
for joining this session of ELO today.
I'm very excited to be here.
My name is Jeremy Andriano.
And my very recently completed M.A.
thesis research was centered around
platform studies— a broad platform
studies inspired comparative
analysis of the digital
writing platforms Twine and Inky,
with a specific interest in the ways
that they can be used in creative
writing classrooms that kind of foreground
literary, aesthetic,
or rhetorical uses of the hyperlink
and downplay computer
and technical aspects.
And I should say, even though this is ELO
(un)supervised, this research
was very well supervised by Dr.
Jason Boyd.
Thank you for being here today.
And I'd also like to thank ComCult’s
faculty.
And just,
I was honored to call my defense chair.
And just an endless source of
hope and encouragement.
Monique Tschofen is also here. So
thank you.
But I think I can move pretty quickly.
I know most of you or all of you
are aware of each of these tools.
They're both digital authoring platforms
for writing interactive hypertext,
and they're both great for use
in the classroom for teaching students
who are new to this kind of writing
for a lot of the same reasons,
like the qualities
that they have in common, make them great
for beginner and classroom use.
They've both demonstrated a dedication
to remaining open source ish
and being freely available,
and they do so through different methods
and for slightly different reasons.
But they have that in common.
They both make use of a very easy
to grasp markup language for creating
and structuring hypertext, for creating
the nodes and linking them together.
That can be grasped within
a single session, but they're both capable
of layering on complex programing logic,
and they both have ample
tutorial material available for students
to expand and learn that as they go.
That's not something I would recommend
starting with in the classroom.
And lastly, they both publish
to sort of a default appearance.
They're easily shareable as HTML.
Writers don't have to do any additional
formatting or HTML configuring in order
to make a playable version
and share it with other people.
So new writers can do this quickly.
But for all these similarities,
these platforms are really—
they're quite distinct.
They both let writers
use hyperlinks to make meaning in creative
and expressive ways, but they do
so through very different methods.
And this creates advantages
and disadvantages
depending on what the writer
is trying to accomplish.
What Skains refers to as key creative
capacities of each of these platforms.
And with Twine and Inky,
I find that these differences
can actually be really useful
in demonstrating,
especially for new students,
some really fundamental concepts
for writing interactive literature,
but then also these different approaches
taken by each of these platforms.
They align with some interactive genres
better than others.
They accommodate different writing styles
and different learning styles.
So, you know, like educators,
like Lyle Skains and Amy Letter
and others, you know, they stress
the teaching technology is hard.
We shouldn't be teaching the technology.
And I'm not suggesting that students
or even instructors
need to learn both of these platforms,
but having a basic understanding
of both of them can help decide where
to expend your energy,
and it can help you direct your students
as to where they might want to spend
their energy for any given project.
And this is most apparent
when we look at Marie-Laure
Ryan's several interpretive modes
or metaphors,
or the ways hyperlinks can be used to
represent different things for the reader,
giving more meaning than simply advancing
a page or clicking through a database.
And one of the most prominent modes
in use is,
of course, the spatial metaphor
in which the text is a territory
and the links are roads
between those passages.
And those passages
can be representative of different things.
They can be locations in a story.
They can be topics of conversation
or subjects between two characters.
Or they might
just be the parts of an academic essay.
But at its very foundation, Twine embodies
the spatial conceptualization
of hypertext, and its entire interface
is designed to let the writer
visualize the passages
in spatial relation to one another.
This is demonstrated perfectly
by Porpetine’s “Howling Dogs,” which
demonstrates Twine's natural alignment
with the spatial modes of hypertext.
We see on the left the famous hub
passage, the room of dark metal.
It's focused almost exclusively
on the spatial relationship
between the objects and other rooms,
the links
that are spread throughout the text,
and they invite the reader to explore
those spaces, to kind of probe and poke.
And then on the right,
I've put together just a simple mock
up of what
the view of this passage might look like,
with the passages arranged
according to their described positions.
But this—
Aaron Reed in “50 Years of Text
Games” puts together this great
visual map of “Howling Dogs,” and
I don't want to spend too much time on it.
But I think many of you actually know
this story
intimately.
I researched a lot of— So.
But basically we see the room of dark
metal starts here, and then the reader
shuffles through the activity room,
and then the story is told across
five vignettes.
And as Reed points out,
the last vignette, Empress,
you can really kind of see the long linear
path that it takes.
And if the reader,
when the reader finally pokes
and probes the right ways, you end up
at the true ending of the story.
But there's all these potential pitfalls
that take you back to the beginning.
This just demonstrates
how spatial “Howling Dogs” is.
It really is.
Like,
for those of you who haven't read it,
it's a fantastic experience of it really.
You are feeling your way in the dark and
it is encouraging you to find a way out.
And it's a beautiful experience
when it works.
Perhaps a better way
to kind of demonstrate “Howling Dogs”’s
close relationship with the Twine platform
and its dependance
on spatial interpretations of hyperlinks
though, is to think about writing it
using a different tool.
So this is what the room of dark
metal might look like
if it were created with Inky.
We'll go into this in a bit more detail,
but when you write with Inky, you write in
lines, and ordered lines that are read in
what an Ink story thinks of as its flow.
And here you can create passages,
and this is what it would look like
to create links that lead
to different passages that then you could,
further down in the script, describe
the text of each of these passages.
And this is what Inky’s
default presentation would look like
to the reader.
And the big thing it misses here
is there's no natural way to incorporate
the links within the text in an Ink story
the way you can in a Twine story.
So again,
you could create the similar effect
and go to the different nodes,
but you lose that kind of key element.
To what?
To what makes “Howling Dogs” what it is.
And this is because when you're writing
with Inky, Inky aligns better with what
Marie-Laure Ryan thinks of as the theater
or the performative interpretation
of hypertext.
Or I think of it as almost a temporal
thought of hypertext,
where you're moving through a story,
a linear plot in order with branches.
As we see here, Ryan compares
this kind of hypertext
to a stage performance, like a script
that's being read that occasionally asks
the reader to make decisions about
how the performance is going to proceed.
So let me see— on the left here,
as I said, it's written as numbered lines.
You introduce choices
for the reader that then appear.
You test over here, and then what happens
if each of the choices are selected—
is filled in underneath?
Again, I don't
want to go too far into technique here,
but it is a very different writing process
than thinking spatially within Twine.
And this is again personified
by kind of a foundational work.
The Ink scripting language
was essentially developed as a development
tool while Inkle Studios
was creating “80 Days.”
So it makes perfect sense
that they're intrinsically tied.
Ink is designed to write stories
that are presented like stories,
which are downstream branching narratives
that move in one direction
and allow the reader
to make selections of text
that then gets added and read
into that performance of the text.
And so we just hear some screenshots
of the way, like dialog
choices are presented to the reader.
Here again,
Aaron Reed dedicates his 2014 entry
in “50 Years of Text Games”
to “80 Days” and showcases here.
So this flowchart,
this is very different than the one
for “Howling Dogs,”
which is kind of meant to be explored.
And it's like feeling around walls almost.
Ink stories move in one direction
in this case, you know, travel
literally from east to west.
And, you know, you can see where like
it's like a flowchart.
It branches differently.
It's not meant to be— you're not meant
to backtrack in a single reading.
You make one decision
and you close off other decisions.
And it's interesting.
And Reed points
this out here, that when decided to adapt
Jules Verne's
“Around the World in 80 Days,”
like they chose that plot
because it matched this style
of storytelling
and not the other way around.
Like they knew they wanted to tell a
downstream flowchart, branching narrative.
And they found that because “80 Days”
you have to travel east.
This worked perfectly.
And I just think that really shows
great synergy
and alignment between all these things
like the software,
the story they're trying to tell,
and then the way they tell it.
I'm going to move a little quickly here.
But this is, you know, if
being able to spread links around
in making an explorable screen is Twine’s
bread-and-butter, Ink’s
bread-and-butter is being able
to let the reader select
the text that then gets added.
It creates this back and forth
collaborative text generating
kind of sensation
for between author and reader.
And so again,
this is a close up of “80 Days.”
You have like three options
of the next line.
That can be
when the reader selects the first one.
You see that text is read
right into the plot or into the display.
The other two choices go away,
and then there's even more text
that the reader didn't know was going
to be there, and it leads to the next one.
And it's a
constant process
of co-creation of the manuscript
when you're playing through “80 Days.”
And again,
I'm not going to go into too much detail.
I think a lot of you know how to do this
better than I do myself, but
this is a demonstration of how like, it's
the simplest, most elegant mechanic
that Inky allows the Ink
scripting language and by— you know,
by extension, its editing software, Inky
allows the writer to come up with this.
And this demonstration
just shows how you can keep
your dialog punctuation consistent.
Anything that appears before the brackets
here will be in the choice,
and also in the resulting text.
What's in the brackets will only appear
in the choices as the link is there,
and then everything afterwards is
what appears after the reader
makes that selection. So
in practice it looks like this.
You know, like, no,
I couldn't eat another bite.
This is punctuated correctly.
And then here we see if that's selected,
it turns into the appropriate comma,
then the dialog brackets
and then finishes with the attribution.
This is just a really specific example to
kind of show like I can't express enough.
I didn't go through it
to even try and demonstrate it.
But doing this is— it involves a lot
more work if you're doing it within Twine.
Certainly not that it's impossible,
but it's cumbersome.
And this is what Inky was designed to do,
and Twine was not.
So that makes sense.
So again,
this whole presentation is kind of
to point out that there's
lots of these kind of examples where
if you're helping students
learn about hypertext
for the first time, it can be helpful
to know if they want to write—
And you can tell them it's helpful
to know up front if they want to write
branching dialog trees,
or if they want to write
if style explorations like go north,
go east, go west— like that
will impact
which platform they should use.
And you know,
they can use it
just while they work on that project
and learn something else
for a different project.
And it also might just appeal
to different students in different ways.
Some people might want to structure
their hypertext graphically in Twine
and then fill things in, and others might
just like to free write prose,
which I think Inky works better for.
And it's just those kind of things
I kind of want to focus on.
It's really what I came to.
I think it's really fascinating.
And, you know, frankly, I
think there's evidence that Inky is kind
of still underrepresented in this space.
And Twine for, you know,
lots of reasons is very represented.
And so it's just good to spread the word
that they do the same thing differently.
Like in “An Educator’s
Guide to Interactive Digital Narrative”
last year, they collected 45 syllabi
from a lot of great educators on this and
Twine outnumbers Inky 10-to-1.
Like it's like 31 references versus three.
And so it's
interesting to know about.
Anyway, thank you very much.
I'm kind of rambling here at the end.
I’d talk about this at length
with any of you.
So thank you for joining us today.